Dr. Andy Galpin here
we're back with another episode of five
minute physiology where I take important
topics from things like contrition
exercise strength and conditioning and
physiology and break them down and give
you the needy greedy in five minutes or
less
today's topic lactate metabolism like
they took my favorite molecules of all
time because you can't read a magazine
go to the gym reflect a football game
without hearing someone talked about
lactic acid buildup and are clearing the
lactate out the day after a hard workout
with your still sore or some nonsense
like that and it makes me laugh makes me
feel bad for Portal active because
everyone hates it right it's the bane of
your existence to some reason why you
failed so I wanted to make this short
video to help you understand a little
bit more about lactate so you understand
what it actually is and you can stop
blaming it for all your crappy problems
your athletic problems and now I'm just
gonna give you a quick shot of in this
video if you this excited to hear more
about a check out the 25 minute
remaining 45 minute physiology videos I
mean I liked it but I understand was
basically happening here have to realize
that black CD is is a byproduct of
metabolism so it's only being generated
in other words when you break down
glucose for fuel ok glucose is basically
the same word as sugar or carbohydrate
in this sense right and and in this
particular talk we're talking about
human skeletal muscle on exercise but we
do that we're seeing here is
carbohydrate is the word itself carbon
and hydrate you can see from the picture
here what I'm talking about is glucose
specifically is a six carbon chain so
it's six carbons and six waters garbo
yeah when I break down glucose for
energy that process to call glycolysis
ok it splits into two separate three
carbon molecules called pyruvate now I
make a little bit energy here but I had
to invest some into it to get there so
in other words I spent $5 I made $10 so
I net gain five bucks now what you're
gaining this particular cases some
energy
used to form a molecule called Google
ATP ATP is the energy currency for all
of biology human not human does it
really matter fact it's the same
currency they using your red blood cells
to generate energy your brain your
skeletal muscle so you can see we make a
little bit ETP right over here in the
corner ok now we realize that we spent
five we gained 10 we didn't $5 I can't
live a $5 so we're not really trying to
make ATP here we're trying to make
pyruvate so that we can use that to make
them more EGP later if we have oxygen
available we can ship the pyruvate to
the mitochondria that can be converted
into another little molecule that can go
through thing called the TCA or citric
acid cycle then go on to electron
transport chain and that'll generate up
to launch of ATP in fact it's probably
10 or 20 for the ATP created here and we
went through glycolysis and the very
beginnings this is the real endgame
unfortunately this process doesn't work
if i dont have the option is there is a
requirement to go in the mitochondria
and that's a requirement of course of a
row vector oxidative metabolism so what
your body says it's ok look what all do
is start shifting pyruvate over to
something else now we have to understand
she is what hydrogen is kinder gentler
often referred to as a proton which is H
plus thats asset so pH at which stands
for potential hydrogen in other words if
you have a lot of free-floating acid a
free-floating hydrogen you are acidic ok
so you start taking your pyruvate East
are saying year ago I know of dinner in
a bunch of acid picture yourself on that
awful paradigm bike right that's in our
house we have a saying that there's no
winning with your time only losing its
the worst exercising every its awesome
adjustments picture yourself you're on
the air and I you doing something like
twenty seconds as hard as you can twenty
seconds off and you do ten rounds out or
something like we did the other day and
you generate a bunch of
asset what you can do the start
attaching that asset to the pyruvate now
because it's not free floating around it
doesn't cause an acidic environment when
we take a pyruvate and attach an H plus
two hydrogen protons we call that new
molecule liked it really is it's a
pirate but that's holding on to higher
than for you so not only is likely not
causing all of your problems don't blame
it for all your weekend standards it's
actually being a buffer in other words
it's stopping you from becoming acidic
because it is holding on to a hundred
and proved I can also learn because it
is simply it is just pyruvate with
hydrogen if I can bring some 02 into the
arena I can combine a couple of
hydrogens with that option I just
brought in and make h2o and so I can
pure hydrogen back off of the lactate
combined with a to make water and it
once I've left the hydrogen I'm not back
in my pyruvate state which is an amazing
former sugar it can also be used as a
homeowner signaling molecule to tell the
rest of your body and other tissues for
a system what's going on so we can ship
lactate to other exercising muscles that
aired I don't burn really hard on my
qualms I can ship lactate to say my
shoulders or something like that they
can strip the hydrogen by combining with
oxygen and make them give themselves
some free sugar we do the same thing at
the heart and the same thing actually
what the liver in a process called the
quarry cycle we actually go through
gluconeogenesis and we take to lactate
combining together and make a brand-new
glucose molecule what some of the recent
research is actually showing is at your
brain will do the same thing so your
brain that we know primarily runs off of
glucose metabolism and since the lactate
is basically a broken down glucose if we
have watched in our brain we can combine
it make water make pyruvate and power
your brain this is probably why we know
that things like cognitive function
memory are improving kids or people
taking final exams
Sams or perform better job when you work
out really hard you are directly
creating lactate which directly fuels
your brain many questions about this let
me know on social media at the Dr NE
Galpin if not on my website you can go
to my website to check out more of these
times of videos
anti-government dot com